Nicholas Steffen

https://www.linkedin.com/in/nicholassteffen1 516-456-1214

I am a software developer with over 5 years experience building frontend and backend products, external integrations, and internal tools. I've learned multiple languages on the job, and pride myself in ramping into a productive team member quickly and efficiently. I love to learn, contribute and teach. I chase after the feeling of solving a hard problem

Skills and Languages: Java, Typescript/Javascript (React, Vue, Node, Express), Python, C++, MySQL, Postgres, MongoDB, Docker (containerization), Ansible, ElasticSearch, Bash, Redis, Version Control(GitHub, Bitbucket, Jira/Confluence, Clearcase), Windows, Linux (RHEL), macOs, Agile, CI/CD, Data structures/Algorithm Design, DevOps, NoSQL, HTML/CSS, REST API, Flask, Django

Work Experience

Software Engineer

ClearlyRated Portland, OR (remote)

June 2021- Nov 2024

- Built full-stack webpages in VueJS and Java for displaying client data, uploading data, and submitting surveys in a SaaS environment, including test-driven development with unit tests and end-to-end testing
- Dockerized MySQL database for seamless local data access, reducing developer onboarding time and allowing for quicker testing and development iterations.
- Developed and optimized Java backend controllers using modern design patterns and data structures to efficiently communicate with front-end web pages, resulting in a reduction in loading times and increase in user engagement.
- Extended a custom context-free grammar tool to parse uploaded CSVs into database contacts with custom filtering and remapping.
- Designed Vue templates to handle contact filtering in concert with Salesforce integrations.
- Upgraded website from Flask to Quart in order to handle async requests.

Software Engineer II

Raytheon Portsmouth, RI

Aug 2018-June 2021

- Developed a Python software suite to monitor and communicate with hardware devices over SNMP.
- Implemented a Python interface with existing Java code using Redis to communicate between two services to integrate new Python modules into legacy code.
- Wrote Python modules to query SQL databases for device statistics using pyodbc to monitor for potential device failures.
- Created Python module leveraging Redis to populate a message queue interacting with Java code to issue safety commands to hardware devices to prevent failures.
- Contributed team effort to convert existing Java codebase to C++ implementation and develop unit tests for the newly converted code.

Millwork Software Consultant

Computer Associates Inc. Smithfield, RI

June 2016-Aug 2018

- Worked closely with customers to create reports and screens to display customers sales and purchasing data.
- Adapted current Windows desktop software to be used on the web according to clients design specifications, allowing the client to open up their sales and quotes to be accessible to their customers online.
- Worked directly with clients to modify the base software package to better suit business needs.

Software Developer Intern

Farsounder Warwick, RI

Summer 2015

- Implemented improvements to C++ based map overlays to track GPS position and provide interactive distance and angle information.
- Added tag support and a hash-based dataset lookup to an internal data playback tool to increase productivity.
- Led a research project into the feasibility of using forward-looking sonar as a depth approximation tool.
- Built Python based visualization tools while designing and testing various algorithms as solutions.

Education and Certifications